# JON WAYLAND

# AL EXECUTIVE | MS APPLIED MATH | MBA

## CONTACT

(814) 771-1017

jonwayland47@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/jonwayland www.jonwayland.com

St. Augustine, FL

#### SKILLS

#### Machine Learning - R, Python

- caret
- ROSE
- tidymodels imblearn
- glmnet
- scikit-learn
- e1071
- TensorFlow
- rpart
- NumPy
- recosystem
- pandas
- XGBoost
- statsmodels

#### **Data Wrangling**

- SQL (SQL Server, DB2, Oracle, Hive)
- Web-Scraping (XML, HTML; rvest)
- Regular Expression (R, Python)

### EDUCATION

M.B.A. Entrepreneurship & Analytics **University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign** 2019-2022

M.S. Applied Mathematics Indiana University of Pennsylvania 2012-2014

**B.S. Mathematics** 

Clarion University of Pennsylvania 2008-2012

## CERTIFICATIONS

Al Strategy **Cornell University** 

2023-2024

**Data Science Certificate** HarvardX on edX

2018-2019

Machine Learning Nanodegree Udacity

2016-2017

## PROFILE

Applied Data Science Leader whose team innovates health solutions for under-65 Floridians using machine learning, GenAl, and advanced statistics. Passionate knowledge sharer who evangelizes AI and believes in ethical decision-making. ChatGPT early adopter and super user. Experienced in the fields of healthcare and technology as both a thought leader and practitioner.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

## **Director, Data Science**

Sr. Manager, Data Science (Jan. 2021 - Mar. 2023)

Sr. Data Scientist (Mar. 2020 - Jan. 2021)

Analytics Consultant (Mar. 2019 - Feb. 2020)

#### Florida Blue | GuideWell

2019-Current

- · Authored GuideWell's ML Enterprise Standards consisting of governance, documentation, development, and deployment best practices for practitioners
- Grew team of 1 to team of 8 full-time data scientists and engineers
- Reduced RFP cover letter creation time from 4 hours to 1 minute by integrating a generative AI solution that customizes content
- Saved \$1.5M annually through internalizing 4 commercial predictive models
- Pioneered novel program evaluation methodology contracted to assess all external care management program performance
- Founded WiseWays, an enterprise ID/Strat system and integrated database
  - o 150+ clinical users; 200+ analytics users; 15+ ML models; 15+ data sources
  - o Feeds all commercial care management, rewards, member website, Provider Vista (external app.), and Care Connect (internal app.)
- Led end-to-end implementation on 30+ machine learning products
  - Predicted end-of-life for <u>advanced care</u> as an IC leading to \$20M+ savings by persuading stakeholders to use internal model over vendor's model
  - XGBoost model with neural network-derived features (45% precision)
- Incentivized rapid development on critical models by launching competitions

## **Data Scientist**

#### 2017-2019 **Availity**

- Increased provider service location accuracy by over 5% by embedding ML model into the PDM product
- Led cross-functional team resulting in segmenting Availity's user population
- · Identified a subset of customers with high likelihood of attrition using registration DOW, slope of transaction volume, and login patterns

#### Analyst II

Analyst I (Aug. 2014 - Feb. 2016)

#### WorkPartners | UPMC Health Plan

2014-2017

- Predicted employees with longer return-to-work times after STD claims by combining randomForestSRC, k-means clustering, and logistic regression
- Led the repeatable integration of nine commonly siloed data sources
- Contributed to acquisition of HCMS Group through validation of analytics

## Part-Time Data Science Roles

2012-2020

- Data Science Mentor | Springboard.com
- Freelancing Data Scientist | Upwork.com
- Data Science Community TA | HarvardX
- Statistical Consultant | IUP Applied Research Lab